so
i found a passage in the suitors that
might be
of interest to others
so i thought it's similar to the
uh suit on the dart
called the dart or the sick ward
so the blessed one said this and how is
one undeveloped embody and undeveloped in
undeveloped embody and undeveloped in
mind
there is a case where a pleasant feeling
arises in an ordinary person on being touched
in an ordinary person on being touched
by the pleasant feeling he becomes
impassioned with pleasure
and and is reduced to being impassioned
with pleasure
his pleasant feeling ceases with a
cessation of that pleasant feeling
there arises a painful feeling on being
touched with a painful feeling
he sorrows grieves becomes distraught
when that pleasant feeling had arisen in
him it
invaded his mind and remained because of
his lack of development
of the body when that painful feeling
had arisen in him it invaded his mind
and remained because
of his lack of development of the mind
this is how one is undeveloped in body
and undeveloped mind
so when there's a pleasant feeling why
is it when there's a pleasant feeling
it invades his mind because he's
undeveloped and undeveloped in body
so in regard to in regard to the
pleasure you need to be developed
in the body or developed in regard to
the body
and then regarding the pain you need to
be developed in regard to the mind
that which is deemed pleasant pleasant
that which is which is considered
agreeable is that which is obtainable
through the sensors
so it's fundamentally bodily it pertains
to the body
and pleasure is experienced through the
body the pleasing sight sounds smell
taste touch
now your mind might be delighting in the
prospect of it but even then
you want to be touching these pleasures
with the body so to speak
you want to be consuming food enjoying
music or whatever the pleasure you're
seeking so it is bodily it lands on the body
so it is bodily it lands on the body
like the counterpart of the sense object
are the sense organs
they're the the recipients of of what
the objects have to offer and those objects
objects have to offer and those objects
are agreeable and disagreeable
that's the same for puttugena and for
another there's no difference
there but the difference is that for uh
for a non-arahant
for somebody who is not free from
sensuality the
the pleasure of the senses
the sense organs that enjoy the sense
objects is their pleasure is the pleasure that
is their pleasure is the pleasure that
they delight in
that they cannot remain in different
words that's what means like being touched by
that's what means like being touched by
the pleasure you can't prevent that so
there is a
pleasing sight just the reason i saw it
you can't prevent that so the touch
of the pleasure is there
but that does not necessarily mean that
automatically your mind must be craving
it
delighting in it wanting more of it
seeking it out acting out of it and
everything else that's what i mean we
said in so many talks because
there's so many suitors about it when
the buddha would say like
having seen something heard something
taste something
he doesn't welcome it he doesn't delight
it he doesn't act out of it he doesn't
entertain it not like he prevent he he
prevents it from
from being experienced in the first
place that's not possible
you can restrain yourself and contain
how much of these things will come your
way so you're not overwhelmed
because if you're constantly bombarded
by by by pressure of
pleasing sight sounds multi-status you
won't be able to handle it so yes you
need to be restrained withdrawn
but sooner or later something agreeable
will arise
and the problem is never in those things
that um there are risen they have arisen
the problem is in you
not being able to remain unmoved by it
so that's how you develop yourself in
regard to your own body
because the extent of your body is the
extent of your centrality
all these sense objects in the world the
variety of them
all of that is unified by the pleasure
that's experienced only through this
body so in other words all you can experience
so in other words all you can experience
is your sense organs
experiencing sense objects you have no
direct line with the sense objects
line with the sense objects
you do so only when you have fully
assumed the ownership and you stop
seeing basically the sense organs for what they
basically the sense organs for what they
are then all you see is me
and things i want but any wanting any
pursuit any central engagement uh is only on the
any central engagement uh is only on the
basis of the sense organs providing you
with it
so being developed in regard to the
sense organs means being developed in
regard to your own body
all of that is within that framework of
your sixth sense basis that's why it's
often referred to as
as bases of fields the um ayatona's
in the suttas it's very through which
the sites
manifest but people are obviously
generally not aware of their sense
organs in the true nature
so all they see is just sense objects so
then whether it's
sensuality pleasing me or or aversion
displeasing me and so on you know it's
all projected out there in the world
i'm like oh this is the cause of it this
is this is what upsets me this is what
pleases me
but fundamentally just your eyes are
upset or displeased
or or pleased and and delighting in
something that they've seen that's the whole
that they've seen that's the whole
simile of the five animals
whereby you have no saying what those
animals want to eat
and what do they deem agreeable but you
have a saying whether you allow them to
go there or not
so being developed in regard to the
animals means being developed in regard
to the body
so when those animals do experience
pleasure oh look they saw something
exciting if you're developed in regards
to the body
means the excitement of those animals
cannot overwhelm you
in other words they cannot take charge
so when they do see something or hear
something or touch something agreeable
you see it for what it is it's just an
agreeable thing of these animals that
they would want to partake in
but you don't lose your perspective so
whether you allow the animals to partake
in it or not
is determined by the wisdom of your
perspective and that's what i mean the clearer that
and that's what i mean the clearer that
becomes the easier the sense restraint
is but fundamentally it's it has to be
dealt with in that sense that the
sensory strain needs to be developed
because you cannot even fathom being developed
you cannot even fathom being developed
in the body
which means not being moved by the
prospects of pleasure or
threats of pain remaining economist
towards it
without having invested effort in sense
restraint beforehand
that's inconceivable
in terms of pain painful feeling
overwhelms well pain pains like if you're
well pain pains like if you're
overwhelmed by the pain means now that's
the more on the mental side
but but fundamentally it's like see when
pleasure touches you
not having enough pleasure it's painful
and now if you want to get rid of that
pain which is not physical now obviously it's
which is not physical now obviously it's
not pertaining to the body
it pertains to the that which body lacks
so it's now your recognition of not
having enough for example of sense
objects that you want
and now you suffer that's mental not
uh wanting to get rid of that mental
that feeling that has arisen as a result
of your mental assumptions and
expectations oh
you're not developed in the mind so when
the pleasure touches you
on the level of the body if that
overwhelms you you're not developing
your body
when the pain touches you on the level
of the mind expectations wanting this
not wanting that
you know as the guru would say um being
paired with things you don't want and
being separated from things you want
it's fundamentally the basis of any
dukkha and that is a that is a mental attitude
and that is a that is a mental attitude
what you want
because like in sensuality say you let
the animals
enjoy sensuality and your mind now wants
more of it
animals still are occupied with what
they are eating tasting touching
but your recognition your loss of right
perspective sees that there could be more of this
sees that there could be more of this
and now that's the mental pain
in regard to not having enough for what
you took for granted
so developed in the mind developed it's
the same principle of development by the
way it's not like these two separate
things if you are developing yourself in the
if you are developing yourself in the
body by
by by sort of not being overwhelmed
by the prospects of pleasure that
manifests in the body
you are developing yourself in the mind
because part of their development is not to
part of their development is not to
resist that
painful feeling of restraint
see for what it is no try to get rid of
it
so if you practice delving into the body
in the body your mind will come along
if your practice development in the mind
your body will come along
so how can you develop yourself in the
mind well let's say something upsets you
well let's say something upsets you
today there is the unpleasant feeling
enduring what is your attitude towards it
so it's mental feeling it's not bodily
your senses are
calm eyes you know you're not agitated
because you're looking at something
disagreeable or hearing something that's really
or hearing something that's really
unpleasant or burning with some
painful sense of touch so bodily you're
fine but you're not fine because something
but you're not fine because something
did upset you
and your mind revolves around it so what
is your attitude towards that
displeasure if it's trying to get rid of it so yeah
if it's trying to get rid of it so yeah
there you go so that means that you
already kind of
if you're trying to get rid of it means
you don't want to see it for what it is
you just want it to not be there because
you basically and act entitled as if you
basically and act entitled as if you
have a right to not experience these
things which means you don't really
understand the mind
and you certainly take trying to take
control of it in that
in that uh appropriated sense oh this is
mine i don't want this to be here i'm
the ruler controller here
but if you were the ruler controller
these things would have not arisen
in the first place things you have to
deal with but you can be
you can in a way be the master be the
master by removing the ownership
that you don't have to begin with you
can be the master by stop
borrowing money from others and building
your kingdom on top of that
because when they're coming to collect
what you owe them you have to give them
your kingdom so
you are not a master ever but if you
build your kingdom
not on borrowed gold and valuables then
nobody can take that away
so you develop yourself in the mind by
first and foremost not resisting that
mental film not trying to get rid of it
so if you you start developing yourself
in the body by being sense restrained
then the mind will start to rebel
against it
sensory strain will will be felt
unpleasantly not enough pleasure it will all be felt
not enough pleasure it will all be felt
on a mental level
if you don't resist that now you're now
developing yourself in the mind
now you might ask how long how long do i
have to not resist that
indefinitely that's the attitude
that needs to be developed it's not like
i do this for a week
then all the problems will be sorted and
then i'll go back to my life
as an enlightened person no you are
reshaping pretty much the way you exist because
pretty much the way you exist because
the way you exist is flawed
it's based on a nietzsche it's based on
um
appropriation it's based on gratuitous
ownership upadhana holding all these
things that
one must get rid of if one wants to be
free from suffering
so you have to have the attitude of i'll
never resist pain
doesn't that doesn't mean like i'll
never move if my if my body aches
physically but mentally when there is any form of
but mentally when there is any form of
mental discomfort
i will not try to get rid of it for its
own sake
in other words you want to be practicing
how to be unmoved unpressured
by the pressure by things that pressure
you and for that your lifestyle needs to
change sensory strength virtue sealer and so on
sensory strength virtue sealer and so on
as we covered in so many previous talks
but then on top of that when you do
experience this discomfort
uh of the mental kind mind resisting
there is that's where the work is the
untrained mind resists
like like a wild monkey i don't want
this and he kicks and screams
even more than the other senses do
that's what i said the mind is the
hardest to tame
but you can't aim it if you have set up
some perimeter
sense restraint so there is no spilling
over over that
so your behavior is kept in check and
then here things will come up
and that's women you don't even need to
be seeking out things to disturb
yourself with
to practice all you need to do is
restrain your other senses and that's
already going to be a disturbance
for a mind that's not free from
sensuality all you need to do is
don't go and seek company and careless
chit chat and pointless talk
live in solitude for somebody who hasn't
developed that that's
order they're going to be a disturbance
mind will already be resisting that
because mind wants things more depends
on engagement and so on
you feel the vacuum that you vote you
know this
craving well yeah yeah the craving needs
to maintain if you stop maintaining it
it's going to be
felt like a vacuum but again if you
if you sustain it if you don't break the
precepts that vacuum will evaporate
and then the pressure will go with it
and then you will actually start
preferring solitude preferring sense
restraint preferring non-disturbance and you will
preferring non-disturbance and you will
have no problem
when unpleasant feeling arises in your
mind to not resist it
because why as it would have said
because now
you know it as impermanent you see it as
unownable and that's more than enough for you to
and that's more than enough for you to
not suffer on account of it
so when people keep saying oh yeah it's
impermanent it's permanent yet they
still suffer
means they don't seem permanent for what
it is it's okay they just try to apply
the impermanence
onto things that bother them so the
things stop bothering
bothering them but you can't do that
you're trying to practice on your own
terms that's how it works
so first you need to stop resisting it
indefinitely and
infinitely
and accept that pain as unchangeable and
now you
will have to endure it how long
no idea it's like you're you have to
decide that your
mode of being from now onwards is
non-craving you know it's a mode of non-craving
you know it's a mode of non-craving
forever
yeah and now everything else
you put put aside over what about this
what about this buddha said you must say
this you must say yeah all of things
that would have said you should see
you can see on the basis of non-craving
so if you adhere to non-craving
non-resisting the displeasure
not welcoming pleasure so you don't go
towards pleasure you don't try to argue
on the pain
but for what is the reason you remain
mindful of it for as long as it endures
what pleasure or pain that arises on the
basis of sensory strength and virtue
that's that's your taming ground
within that now you need to tame your
mind and not act
towards pleasure and not act trying to
get rid of the pain
if you have not been acting by body and
by speech now you can start seeing even
mental acts of hoping
for it to not be there or hoping for it
to stay longer
you'll see it and by seeing it for what
it is you're already
addressing it correctly enduring it
infinitely yeah doesn't matter whether how if it
yeah doesn't matter whether how if it
lasts only for five minutes
or five days doesn't matter your
attitude is
this will be endured infinitely and i
must not have a problem with that
because if i have a problem with that
i'm trying to take the ownership back
and it's because of that ownership that
i suffer in the first place
so that's the place you want to be at
is as you said before to be able to
not be moved to be able to endure
any pressure without being upset or
bothered by it so
which is so it doesn't matter if there
is pressure anymore you want
you don't want to be at peace when
there's no pressure you want to be
attracted when there is utmost pressure yes your
when there is utmost pressure yes your
goal is not to not have pressure
your goal is to not be moved by anything
so whether pressure is there or not
you remain indifferent
so that's why you wouldn't be able to
seeking out pressure to prove anything
nor would you be afraid of the pressure
if it does come because again
hoping that no pressure will ever hoping
that no pressure will come yet
one part of being developed in the body
is knowing the extent of the pleasure
you know like say you wanna you want to
eat something agreeable
you get intoxicated by the object i food
when you forget that the final outcome
is just
food in your stomach so just passing
through the
the sense of taste and that's it
that is it can it cannot be more than
that so if you don't forget that before you
so if you don't forget that before you
even start eating
you will not be able to be as
intoxicated with the objects of
of your desire that you're eating same
with any other sense
you realize that doesn't matter the
extent of the pleasure you might be able
to get from it it's going to remain
bound with literally with the physicality of
with literally with the physicality of
your sense orga
it cannot be more than that you are
making it more than that
by forgetting that it's ultimately only
pertaining to the eye
ear mouth body nose and so on
so that's that means pretty much even
before you engage with the pleasure
you already have the end of that
pleasure you already see where it ends
so that's what buddha described he
understands the extent of gratification
to any sight is always bounded by
extent but i just want to see this thing
that i never seen before
outcome of that will be that which you
experienced many times before
i seeing agreeable doesn't matter what
only when you forget
that general nature you get pulled by
the specificity
of a thing of a sight sounds melting but
i never tasted
that an agreeable taste exactly
what is the value of that agreeability
so you never had the
ability oh no i had it all the time
there you go it's the same thing
so not losing the sight of that context
will significantly sort of reduce the amount
significantly sort of reduce the amount
of
your intoxication with the object and
the variety that's what i said
the the the reason why man's desires
grow is like
the variety diversity diversity of sight
sound smell taste touches
they sort of induce more and more desire
in the mind that's not developed
in regard to the body because you fail
to understand it doesn't matter the
variety of the sense object
the sense base is the same and it's
measured by agreeable
disagreeable or neither that's it
so if if if if that's kept in mind
that's already
you're already seeing at least to some
degree clearer
the extent of gratification or you
cannot pass this it cannot be more than
that the pleasure i can get through this
the pleasure i can get through this
cannot cannot exit
this framework of of the eye organ
it naturally which already devalues it
for seeing
what it is oh it's just that but when
you forget that that's when you get
pulled in the
variety of things and and that's
infinite the permutations of sense of sense
the permutations of sense of sense
objects are infinite
so that's how i the desire feels
infinite equally infinite in in a mind
that's not practice restrained
it just feels insatiable because you
placed it upon things that are infinite
so in that sense it is insatiable
but all you need to do is step back onto
the context of the nature
doesn't matter how infinite your desire
and prospect of pleasure is
what is it side sound smell taste touch
it's bound with that sense and to that
extent all you're going to have is
pleasing sight pleasing sound
doesn't matter how how greatly pleasing
it still
just felt pleasantly that's it
and and it cannot step outside of that
it cannot be more than that so the
gratification gratification has been
this has been understood to its full extent
you see the extent seeing the extent of
ratification means basically seeing the
extent of the danger as well
and then seeing the way out
like you really want to go and i don't
know listen to some music or
or something
the desire towards that specific object
is their present in urine you don't need
to deny that
all you need to do is broaden your
perspective and pretty much recollect
and remind yourself
that it cannot become more
than a pleasing sound sound that is
pleasing to these ears so your ears
to these ears so your ears
the pleasure the pain in regard to it or
neither is pretty much the extent of any sense
is pretty much the extent of any sense
objects that can gratify you or upset
you and so on
it's this this physical body
so yes you're saying what have like what
haven't you
experienced then already i mean you
might not have
have experienced the worst kind of pain
well the way you should say that is like
you should you should cease you should
stop measuring um your experience by what
measuring um your experience by what
have you experienced specifically and
what you have what
you haven't experienced and start
measuring it on that general level
like what feeling is there in regard to
this specific thing
not what specific thing is there that i
have this feeling on account of
yeah you want to be start you want to
start putting that feeling first as a
framework so in regard to side sound smell taste
so in regard to side sound smell taste
touches and thoughts
you don't want to be focused on the
content of those organs of those objects
of those organs of those objects
you want to be seeing how you feel in
regard to it
regardless of what the object is
and then you start recognizing that well
that's how you learn then to measure
your experience by that
more general framework and not be pulled
by the specific things that come to your
senses so next time if you train your mind in
so next time if you train your mind in
that pleasing sight this pleasing sound
doesn't matter all you see is
there is pleasure mind is leaning
towards it
there is this pleasure mind leaning away
from it
but if you see the object first and then
the pleasure or the pain as a result
of that you're not you're not going to
see how your mind is already leaning
towards or away
from it you'll be concerned with the
object because this and then again you see
because this and then again you see
you have a attention experience and you
have your mind leading towards it
and a painful and and so on and again
and again and again so it's the same
same thing the same principle constantly
occurring i mean
it's you know you get be quite
dispassionate well no even that's that's usually what
well no even that's that's usually what
happens like when people over indulge in
sensuality if they have access to it usually
if they have access to it usually
depression is the outcome of it
because you just go numb through that
constant repetition because yeah
even even with all the wrong views and
all the central assumptions the reality
starts becoming more and more obvious
it's the same
one or hundred it's the same same
feeling that's there in regard to it and that
that's there in regard to it and that
becomes
depressing for a mind that still wants
more becomes very liberating for the mind
becomes very liberating for the mind
that wants to free itself from it but
that's not always the direction that
people will take
yes in seeing seeing that same pleasure
that same pain
and that same mental movement happen
again and again
i say that's what i said is that it's
enough for you to become dispassionate
just seeing that sure sure if there is
any wisdom
that would be enough for you to to turn
towards this passion and valuing it yeah
because i've had that yeah
what i'm trying to say is it's not going
to happen automatically so people
shouldn't expect oh if i just
scratch myself scratch the central edge
to the point of
feeling sick about it then i'll turn to
this passion
not necessarily wisdom is required to
start valuing this passion oh yeah
no you but you don't see that level if
you're engaging with
sensuality you don't see that general
level yeah
so how would you for example measure
then
prospects of bodily pleasure
[Music] what would you do
say there's something very agreeable
waiting for you over there when we
finish this
what do you do do not go there
do you shut your eyes nose
how would you deal with it
i'm just well i would be
any feeling whatever i'm feeling now and
if i go
there and i feel but there's already so
okay yeah yeah exactly so that's my
point so
all you're not there knowing that
there's something there
but i think this would be something
there the prospect of it thought that he
felt now
so yeah so you don't need to oh when i
go there i'll be all i need to do is be
careful in regards to the prospect here
through the framework of being careful
about the prospect here when you're
there in that actual prospect that's now
in that actual prospect that's now
actual uh
you're already careful because you
already see this is the gateway for
for for any pleasure to come same or
there is something bad there waiting for
you but the badness is felt now exactly
but the badness is felt now exactly
exactly the badness is felt now so
that's when people stop practicing sense
restraint it's always going to be mind
will be there
in regards to things they're saying no
to and so on but you realize
yeah okay that's how you start but it's
actually it's already here
although i'm not engaging with those
things i'm already feeling it here
that's the gateway
so i should not be i must never see that
here that no i should develop myself in
regard to feeling i'm feeling right here
right now
in regard to the prospect of something
to be seen or heard or smell to taste
the time because
you're already welcoming you're already
existing so that's what i mean instead of being
so that's what i mean instead of being
concerned with the particulars
with the content of your experience you
start saying
you start putting the present and during
feeling first in regard to the content
so in this case the contact content is
still like not quite defined or there is
like not quite defined or there is
something there
probably pleasant waiting for you
but the feeling here that's agreeable on
account of that it's already defined
as far as the feelings can be defined in
itself you recognize it
there is agreeability just by the simple
knowledge that there might be something agreeable
that there might be something agreeable
there for me on a more specific level
but that feeling of agreeability doesn't
change that's the gateway through which
you then accept
the more specific agreeability of these
sense objects and so on
so you don't need to wait to go there to
deal with it
you can deal with that feeling here and
now not delighted not welcome it
remain careful in regard to it doesn't
matter what's there if you end up even
seeing it
and so on if it's nothing unwholesome
you won't be affected by it
because you haven't perverted that or
you haven't put the object of your
senses first
you remain seeing it on the level of the
feeling enduring
and that's that that whole suit that we
did like entering the forest
full of bobs and thorns um so you have
to enter it
it's just thrown everywhere
how would you do it very carefully
move move go slowly
so that's the important recognition is
to see that it's always here and now
things to be dealt with are always here
and now
and if you have future fear or fear
about the future or delight in the
future or
worry about the past the only reason
you're engaged in those directions is
because here and now it's either felt
pleasantly and you're welcoming it
indulging it delighting in it
entertaining it
or it's felt unpleasantly and you're
trying to get rid of it
which means you're not seeing where the
problem is
you're still on the level of the content
of your experience
not the context as we as we covered in
we covered everything in overtones anyway